This story starts with these two --
بدأت هذه القصة مع هذين الاثنين --
my kids.
طفلاي.
We were hiking in the Oakland woods
بينما كنا نتنزه في غابات أوكلاند،
when my daughter noticed a plastic tub of cat litter in a creek.
لاحظت ابنتي وعاء بلاستيكيا مخصصا لفضلات القطط مرمى في جدول ماء.
She looked at me and said,
نظرت إلي وقالت،
"Daddy?
"أبي؟"
That doesn't go there."
"ليس ملائمًا أن توضع هذه هنا."
When she said that, it reminded me of summer camp.
عندما قالت ذلك، ذكّرتني بالمخيم الصيفي.
On the morning of visiting day,
في صباح يوم الزيارة،
right before they'd let our anxious parents come barreling through the gates,
مباشرةََ قبل ترك أبوانا المتلهفين كانوا يأتون مسرعين نحو البوابات،
our camp director would say,
كان يقول لنا مدير المخيم،
"Quick! Everyone pick up five pieces of litter."
"ليسرع الجميع بالتقاط خمس قطع من القمامة."
You get a couple hundred kids each picking up five pieces,
لديك مائتي فتى وكلُُ منهم يجمع خمس قطع،
and pretty soon, you've got a much cleaner camp.
وبعد وقت قليل جدا يصبح المخيم أكثر نظافة.
So I thought,
لذا فكرت في،
why not apply that crowdsourced cleanup model to the entire planet?
لمَ لا نطبق نموذج النظافة المعتمدة على المساهمة الجماعية في الكوكب بأكمله؟
And that was the inspiration for Litterati.
وكان هذا مصدر الإلهام لتطبيق "ليتراتي".
The vision is to create a litter-free world.
تكمن الرؤية في عالم خال من القمامة.
Let me show you how it started.
دعوني أريكم كيف كانت البداية.
I took a picture of a cigarette using Instagram.
التقطت صورة لسيجارة مستخدما انستجرام.
Then I took another photo ...
ثم التقطت صورة أخرى ...
and another photo ...
ثم صورة أخرى ...
and another photo.
ثم صورة أخرى.
And I noticed two things:
ولاحظت أمرين:
one, litter became artistic and approachable;
أولهما أنها أصبحت قطعة فنية ويمكن بلوغها؛
and two,
والأمر الثاني،
at the end of a few days, I had 50 photos on my phone
بعد أيام قليلة، كان عندي 50 صورة على هاتفي
and I had picked up each piece,
و أني جمعت كل قطعة منها،
and I realized that I was keeping a record
وأدركت أني أسجل رقما قياسيا
of the positive impact I was having on the planet.
للتأثير الإيجابي الذي أتركه على الكوكب.
That's 50 less things that you might see,
هذه القطع الخمسون الصغيرة التي قد ترونها،
or you might step on,
أو قد تدوسون عليها،
or some bird might eat.
أو قد يأكلها الطير.
So I started telling people what I was doing,
لذا بدأت أخبر الناس عما أفعله،
and they started participating.
وبدأوا في التفاعل معي.
One day,
وفي يومِِ ما،
this photo showed up from China.
ظهرت هذه الصورة من الصين.
And that's when I realized
وعندها أدركت
that Litterati was more than just pretty pictures;
بأن "ليتراتي" أكبر من كونه مجرد صور جميلة؛
we were becoming a community that was collecting data.
كنا عبارة عن مجموعة تجمع بيانات.
Each photo tells a story.
وكل صورة تحكي قصة ما.
It tells us who picked up what,
وتخبرنا من الذي التقط وماذا التقط،
a geotag tells us where
والإشارة المكانية تخبرنا أين حدث ذلك
and a time stamp tells us when.
والطابع الزمني يخبرنا متى كان ذلك.
So I built a Google map,
لذا أنشأت خريطة على جوجل،
and started plotting the points where pieces were being picked up.
وبدأت في تحديد العلامات حيث التُقطت القطع.
And through that process, the community grew
وخلال هذه العملية، زادت المجموعة
and the data grew.
وزادت البيانات.
My two kids go to school right in that bullseye.
يذهب أطفالي إلى المدرسة وهذا هدفهم.
Litter:
القمامة:
it's blending into the background of our lives.
يمتزج هذا في خلفية حياتنا.
But what if we brought it to the forefront?
لكن ماذا لو وضعناها في المقدمة؟
What if we understood exactly what was on our streets,
ماذا لو فهمنا تحديدا ما كان في شوارعنا،
our sidewalks
وفي الأرصفة
and our school yards?
وفي ساحات المدرسة؟
How might we use that data to make a difference?
كيف قد نستخدم تلك البيانات في إحداث فرق؟
Well, let me show you.
حسنََا، دعوني أريكم.
The first is with cities.
الأولى تتعلق بالمدن.
San Francisco wanted to understand what percentage of litter was cigarettes.
أرادت مدينة سان فرانسيسكو تحديد نسبة القمامة الناتجة عن السجائر.
Why?
لماذا؟
To create a tax.
لفرض ضريبة.
So they put a couple of people in the streets
لذا وضعوا مجموعة أفراد في الشوارع
with pencils and clipboards,
ومعهم أقلام وألواح كتابية،
who walked around collecting information
الذين جابوا المنطقة لجمع المعلومات
which led to a 20-cent tax on all cigarette sales.
مما أدى إلى فرض ضريبة قدرها 20 سنتََا على جميع مبيعات السجائر.
And then they got sued
وبعدها قاضتهم
by big tobacco,
شركات التبغ الكبرى،
who claimed that collecting information with pencils and clipboards
الذين ادّعوا بأن جمع المعلومات باستخدام الأقلام و اللوحات
is neither precise nor provable.
ليس دقيقََا ولا مثْبتََا.
The city called me and asked if our technology could help.
اتصل بي مسؤولوا المدينة وسألوا إذا كانت التكنولوجيا الخاصة بنا قد تفيد.
I'm not sure they realized
لست متأكدا إذا أدركوا
that our technology was my Instagram account --
أن تلك التكنولوجيا هي حسابي على انستجرام --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I said, "Yes, we can."
لكني قلت "نعم، نستطيع."
"And we can tell you if that's a Parliament or a Pall Mall.
"ونستطيع إطلاعكم إذا كانت من ماركة "بارلامنت" أو" بول مول".
Plus, every photograph is geotagged and time-stamped,
إضافةََ أن جميع الصور محددة المكان والزمن.
providing you with proof."
مقدمةََ لك الدليل."
Four days and 5,000 pieces later,
أربعة أيام وتم تجميع 5,000 قطعة،
our data was used in court to not only defend but double the tax,
استُخدمت بياناتنا في المحكمة ليس للدفاع فقط بل لمضاعفة الضريبة،
generating an annual recurring revenue of four million dollars
موجدة مكاسب سنوية متكررة تبلغ أربعة ملايين دولار
for San Francisco to clean itself up.
لصالح سان فرانسيسكو لنظافة المدينة.
Now, during that process I learned two things:
الآن وأثناء تلك العملية تعلمت شيئين:
one, Instagram is not the right tool --
الأول، انستجرام ليس الأداة المناسبة--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
so we built an app.
لذا اخترعنا تطبيقََا.
And two, if you think about it,
والثاني، إذا فكرت بالأمر،
every city in the world has a unique litter fingerprint,
لدى كل مدينة في العالم بصمة فريدة للتخلص من القمامة،
and that fingerprint provides both the source of the problem
وتلك البصمة تقدم كلا من مصدر المشكلة
and the path to the solution.
وطريقة حلها.
If you could generate a revenue stream
لو استطعت إيجاد تدفق للمكاسب
just by understanding the percentage of cigarettes,
عن طريق تحديد نسبة السجائر فقط،
well, what about coffee cups
حسنا، ماذا عن أكواب القهوة
or soda cans
أو علب المياه الغازية
or plastic bottles?
أو الزجاجات البلاستيكية؟
If you could fingerprint San Francisco, well, how about Oakland
إذا تمكنت من وضع بصمة علي سان فرانسيسكو، حسنََا، ماذا عن أوكلاند
or Amsterdam
أو أمستردام
or somewhere much closer to home?
أو مكان أقرب كثيرا إلى المنزل؟
And what about brands?
والعلامات التجارية؟
How might they use this data
كيف قد يستخدمون هذه البيانات
to align their environmental and economic interests?
لتنظيم مصالحهم البيئية مع الاقتصادية؟
There's a block in downtown Oakland that's covered in blight.
هناك عقار في وسط مدينة اوكلاند محاط بالآفات.
The Litterati community got together and picked up 1,500 pieces.
تكاتف مجتمع ليتراتي والتقطوا 1,500 قطعة.
And here's what we learned:
وإليكم ما تعلمناه:
most of that litter came from a very well-known taco brand.
أن أغلب هذه القمامة مصدرها علامة تاكو التجارية الشهيرة جدا.
Most of that brand's litter were their own hot sauce packets,
أغلب قمامتها هي أكياس الصلصة الحارة.
and most of those hot sauce packets hadn't even been opened.
ومعظمها لم يُفتح حتى.
The problem and the path to the solution --
المشكلة وطريقة الحل--
well, maybe that brand only gives out hot sauce upon request
حسنََا، قد تقدم هذه العلامة التجارية صلصة حارة عند الطلب
or installs bulk dispensers
أو تضع ماكينات توزيع آلية
or comes up with more sustainable packaging.
أو تتوصل إلى تغليف أكثر استدامة.
How does a brand take an environmental hazard,
كيف تأخذ علامة تجارية خطرا بيئيا،
turn it into an economic engine
وتحوله إلى محرك اقتصادي
and become an industry hero?
وتصبح محط إعجاب في الصناعة؟
If you really want to create change,
إذا أردت حقََا أن تحدث تغييرا،
there's no better place to start than with our kids.
فلا يوجد أفضل من البداية مع أطفالنا.
A group of fifth graders picked up 1,247 pieces of litter
قامت مجموعة من الصف الخامس بجمع1,247 قطعة من القمامة
just on their school yard.
فقط من ساحة المدرسة الخاصة بهم.
And they learned that the most common type of litter
وعرفوا أن أكثر نوع شائع من القمامة
were the plastic straw wrappers from their own cafeteria.
كانت أغلفة المصاصة البلاستيكية من مطعمهم الخاص.
So these kids went to their principal and asked,
لذا ذهب هؤلاء الأطفال إلى مديرهم وسألوه،
"Why are we still buying straws?"
"لم لا نزال نبتاع المصاصات ؟"
And they stopped.
وتوقفوا عن شرائها.
And they learned that individually they could each make a difference,
وتعلموا أن كل فرد منهم يستطيع إحداث فرق،
but together they created an impact.
لكنهم معََا أوجدوا تأثيرََا.
It doesn't matter if you're a student or a scientist,
لايهم إن كنت طالبََا أم عالمََا،
whether you live in Honolulu or Hanoi,
سواءََا تعيش في هونولولو أم في هانوي،
this is a community for everyone.
ينتمي الجميع لهذا المجتمع.
It started because of two little kids in the Northern California woods,
بدأ الأمر بسبب طفلين صغيرين في غابات كليفورنيا الشمالية،
and today it's spread across the world.
واليوم انتشر في جميع أرجاء العالم.
And you know how we're getting there?
وهل تعلمون كيف وصلنا لتلك المرحلة؟
One piece at a time.
قطعة واحدة في كل مرة.
Thank you.
شكرََا لكم.